Our course is about
distributed algorithms,
but this week we won't talk
about distributed things or
algorithmic things.
We will study graph theory,
because we will later need
plenty of it in this course.
In this lecture,
I'll introduce some basic
graph-theoretic concepts
with the help of an example.
In the course material you'll
find the formal definitions
of everything we use here,
but I hope you can follow
this presentation as long as
you are familiar with
the basic concepts
like graphs, nodes, and edges.
I'd like to emphasize that here
all graphs are simple,
undirected graphs.
There is a finite,
nonempty set of nodes,
and a set of edges, and each
edge is a set of 2 nodes.
To illustrate some key ideas,
I'll prove the following theorem:
In any d-regular graph
(where d is at least 1),
a minimum vertex cover is always
a d-approximation of
a minimum dominating set.
Let me decompose this and
explain all words here,
so that we understand
what we claim here.
The degree of a node
is the number of neighbors.
And a graph is d-regular if
all nodes have degree d.
So we are focusing here
on graphs in which
all nodes have the same
number of neighbors.
Here are some examples
of 1-regular graphs,
2-regular graphs,
and 3-regular graphs.
For example, this graph here is
3-regular: if you look at
any node, you'll see that
it has got exactly 3 neighbors.
Good, so now we
understand this part.
Then what about vertex covers?
Let's assume C is
a subset of nodes.
We say that C is a vertex cover
if, for each edge, we have got
at least 1 endpoint in set C.
For example, here this set of
nodes is a vertex cover.
If you take any edge,
you will see that at least one
endpoint is in set C.
You can have both endpoints in C.
But you must have at least 1.
For example, this set of nodes
is not a vertex cover, as we've
got this edge here that doesn't
have any endpoint selected.
So you can think about
vertex covers so that
each node covers all
of its incident edges.
And a set of nodes is a vertex
cover if it covers all edges.
And we say that C is
a minimum vertex cover
if it is a vertex cover
that has the smallest
possible number of nodes.
So for example this one here
is a minimum vertex cover.
It is a vertex cover
with 2 nodes,
and for this graph there is no
vertex cover with fewer nodes.
This one is not
a minimum vertex cover,
because it has got 3 nodes,
while 2 nodes are enough
to cover the graph.
Good, so now we know
what this part means.
Then let's look at this part,
dominating sets.
Let's assume that D
is a subset of nodes.
We say that D is
a dominating set
if each node is in D or has got
at least one neighbors in D.
For example, here this set of
nodes is a dominating set.
If you take any node, either
it is already selected,
or at least 1 of its neighbors
is selected.
For example, this set of nodes
is not a dominating set,
as we've got this node here
that is not selected, and none
of its neighbors are selected.
The intuition here is that
a node can dominate
all of its neighbors.
And a set of nodes is
a dominating set if
all nodes are dominated.
And now D is
a minimum dominating set
if it is a dominating set
that has the smallest possible
number of nodes.
So for example this one here is
a minimum dominating set.
It is a dominating set
with 2 nodes,
and for this graph there is no
dominating set with fewer nodes.
And this one is not
a minimum dominating set,
because it has got 3 nodes,
while 2 nodes are enough
to dominate the graph.
Good, we are making progress, we
know also what this part means.
Finally, we need to understand
approximations.
When we say that set D is
a k-approximation of
a minimum dominating set,
we mean the following.
First, D is a dominating set.
Second, the size of D is
at most k times the size of
the minimum dominating set.
That's it.
That's the full
definition, nothing more.
Please note that
approximations have to be
feasible dominating sets.
It isn't roughly
a dominating set.
It has to be exactly
The only sloppiness is
in the size.
It doesn't need to be
a minimum-size dominating set,
it can be larger by some factor.
For example, this is an example
of a 2-approximation of
a minimum dominating set.
In this graph the minimum
dominating set is 3 nodes.
And here we have
a dominating set with 6 nodes.
Six is at most 2 times 3.
So this is a 2-approximation.
So now we understand all terms.
Let's rephrase the claim
so that it is easier to follow.
We can take any
positive integer d.
And we can take any graph G
that is d-regular.
And we can take any
minimum vertex cover X.
And the claim is that X is also
a d-approximation of
a minimum dominating set.
And to make it more clear,
let's expand it a bit.
Consider any minimum
vertex cover X and
any minimum dominating set Y.
Then we claim that X is
also a dominating set,
and its size is not more than
d times the size of Y.
Does this claim make any sense?
Let's quickly go through
some examples.
Here d = 1.
We have a 1-regular graph.
Here is a minimum vertex cover X
with 1 node,
and a minimum dominating set Y
with 1 node.
It's easy to check that X is
also a dominating set,
and indeed its size is
1 times the size of Y.
Here d = 2.
We have a 2-regular graph.
Here is a minimum vertex cover X
with 2 nodes,
and a minimum dominating set Y
with 1 node.
We can check that X is
also a dominating set,
and its size is 2 times the size
of Y, just like it should be.
And another example for d = 2.
Another 2-regular graph.
A minimum vertex cover X
with 3 nodes,
and a minimum dominating set Y
with 2 nodes.
Again, X is a also
a dominating set,
and its size is at most
2 times the size of Y.
Please note that here we are
doing a bit better,
the size of X is only 1.5 times
the size of Y, but that's fine.
And here d is 3.
And here is an example of
a graph where
a minimum vertex cover
has 3 nodes
and a minimum dominating set
has got 1 node.
Again, the size of X is
at most 3 times the size of Y,
and X is also a dominating set.
And a yet another example here.
A minimum vertex cover
with 4 nodes.
A minimum dominating set
with 2 nodes.
Factor-2 difference,
which is at most 3.
Good, so the claim
at least seems to make sense
in these examples,
and we know also that
the claim is basically
the strongest possible.
In the previous examples we saw
that sometimes the ratio is
exactly d, sometimes less.
Now let's prove this claim!
We need to prove 2 things.
First, we need to prove that
a minimum vertex cover
is also a dominating set.
Second, we need to prove that
a minimum vertex cover is not
that much larger than
the smallest dominating set.
Let's start with the first part.
Let X be any vertex cover.
We don't need to use
the property that it is
a minimum vertex cover here,
so we can just look at
any vertex cover.
We need to show that
X dominates all nodes, that is,
all nodes not in X have at
least one neighbor in X.
To do this, consider any node u.
The graph is d-regular and
d is at least 1,
so node u has got at least one
neighbor, let's call it v.
So in the graph there is
an edge .
And X is a vertex cover,
so it contains at least one
of the endpoints of this edge.
So u is in X, or
if this is not the case,
its neighbor v is in X.
So we are done:
X is a dominating set.
Now comes the more
interesting part.
We need to bound the size of X
in comparison with the size of Y.
We don't need to use
the property that Y is
a minimum dominating set here,
it is enough to show that X
is at most d times as large as
any dominating set,
and then it of course also holds
for the specific case of
a minimum dominating set.
Let's use n to denote the total
number of nodes in the graph.
We will first compare
the size of Y with n,
and then compare
the size of X with n,
and this will give what we want.
Let's start by analyzing set Y,
which is assumed to be
some dominating set.
Let's put some tokens on
the nodes as follows.
Each node in Y puts
one token on itself and
one token on each of
its neighbors.
Because Y is a dominating set,
each node got at least 1 token.
And because all nodes in Y
have exactly d neighbors,
we used d+1 tokens
per node in Y.
So in total the number of
tokens we used
was d+1 times the size of Y.
And because each node
got at least 1 token,
we must have used
at least n tokens.
So n is at most d+1 times
size of Y.
Good, let's keep this inequality
in mind, we'll use it soon.
Let's next analyze set X,
which is assumed to be
a minimum vertex cover.
We'll again put some tokens
but with a twist.
Let's define set A that
consists of those nodes that
are not in the vertex cover.
Now each node in A puts
one token on itself
and one on each neighbor.
So the total number of tokens
is d+1 times the size of A.
And I'm claiming that each node
got at least one token,
so we had to use
at least n tokens.
Why is this the case?
Well, let's image that
there was a node v
that didn't get any tokens.
So v itself has to be
in the vertex cover,
otherwise it would give
a token to itself.
And all neighbors of v have to
be also in the vertex cover,
otherwise they would
give us tokens.
But what would this mean?
All of these edges incident to v
have both endpoints
in the vertex cover X.
If X is a vertex cover,
we could remove v from X,
and it would still be
a vertex cover.
So we could construct
another vertex cover
that is smaller than X.
But we assumed X is
a minimum vertex cover,
so this cannot happen.
So it has to be the case that
all nodes got at least 1 token,
and the number of tokens
is therefore at least n.
So we have that the size of A
is at least n over d+1.
And now we know enough about
the size of X.
It's the complement of A, so its
size is n minus the size of A.
And using this gives this,
so the size of X is at most
d over d+1 times n.
Now let's recall what
I told you to remember.
We already proved that n is
at most d+1 times the size of Y.
So the size of X is
at most d times the size of Y,
which is exactly what
we were supposed to prove!
So a theorem proved.
Why did we do this?
Not because this is an important
result in graph theory,
it certainly isn't.
But because this proof
demonstrates both key concepts
and some useful proof techniques
that we will use in this course.
By the way, it's good to note
that we didn't really ever need
the property that
X is a minimum vertex cover.
We only need to assume that
if you remove any node from X,
it is no longer a vertex cover.
So it was enough to assume that
X is a minimal vertex cover,
that is, you can't remove
any nodes from it.
On the other hand,
if you only assumed
that X is a vertex cover,
this claim is no longer true.
Can you see why?
What's the simplest
counterexample?