Hi everyone,
Today I'll present
a simple and efficient
distributed algorithm
for graph coloring.
Or more precisely,
one algorithm that you can use
as a subroutine when designing
fast graph coloring algorithms.
Let q be any prime number.
The only requirement is that
q is more than 2 times
the maximum degree of the graph.
We will show how to reduce
the number of colors from
q² to q in only q rounds.
So for example, if q is 7,
we can reduce
the number of colors
from 49 to 7 in only 7 rounds.
I'll use q = 7 to
illustrate the idea.
Our input colors are
pairs (a, b), where
both a and b are numbers
between 0 and 6.
So we can handle 7 × 7
possible input colors.
And our output colors are
pairs of the form (0, b).
So there are only 7 possible
output colors when we are done.
Color reduction from 49 to 7.
It's best to visualize nodes
as clocks with one hand.
Value (a, b) means that the hand
is moving at speed a and
it is currently in position b.
So in each step we change
(a, b) to (a, b + a mod 7).
And the algorithm is
really simple:
you stop the clock when you can
do it in a conflict-free manner.
You just switch from (a, b)
to (0, b) whenever this is safe,
when no neighbor is
in position b.
And that's it.
So our possible input colors are
these 49 configurations,
7 speeds, 7 positions.
And when the nodes are running,
their colors change like this.
Clocks are ticking.
Hands are moving at
constant speed.
And neighbors have by assumption
different input colors
so they will start in
different configurations.
Either they start in
different positions.
Or move at different speeds.
Or both.
And our final configurations
are these 7 possibilities.
Clocks are stopped, hands are
in one of 7 possible position.
This is what we are
trying to achieve.
A proper coloring where
all clocks are stopped.
Let's see how the algorithm
works in practice.
Here is a complete graph
with four nodes.
Our input configuration might
look for example like this.
First round.
Check for conflicts.
The top two nodes have their
hands in the same positions,
but the bottom nodes
don't have any conflicts.
Bottom nodes can stop, they set
their speeds to 0, they are done.
Nodes that are still running
move to the next position.
Second round.
Check for conflicts.
Bad luck,
both of the running nodes are
still in conflict with someone,
this time with the nodes
that are already stopped.
No progress.
Advance to the next position.
Third round.
Check for conflicts.
No conflicts left.
Both of the nodes can stop.
We are done.
We have got a new coloring from
a color palette of only 7 colors.
Let's look at another example.
We start like this.
Check for conflicts,
everyone has got conflicts,
everyone moves their hands.
Check for conflicts,
two nodes on the right
conflict with each other,
but the nodes on the left
can stop.
Move hands,
check for conflicts, still bad!
Move hands, check for conflicts,
still bad for the top right node!
The bottom right node can stop.
Move hands, check for conflicts,
now we are finally done.
Good, you get the algorithm.
But does it work correctly?
In the previous example
it already took a while;
could it be the case
that we just keep getting
conflicts forever?
Let's think about this.
Let's look at a node and
one of its neighbors.
Let's first assume that
both of the nodes are running.
As these are neighbors,
their starting positions
or speeds must differ.
Now no matter what are
the speeds of these nodes,
in 7 rounds their hands
are aligned at most once!
If they have different speeds
their hands are aligned
exactly once.
If they run at the same speed,
their hands will be
never aligned.
So if you and your neighbor
are both running, in 7 rounds
you'll have conflicts with
this neighbor at most once.
But what if your neighbor
has stopped?
Well, the same thing,
in 7 rounds you'll have
conflicts with it only once.
So in 7 rounds,
you'll have conflicts
with any specific neighbor
at most twice,
even if it happens to stop
in the middle.
You'll get conflicts at most once
while your neighbor is running.
And at most once
when it's stopped.
And for example here
each node had 3 neighbors.
So let's think about this from
the perspective of any given node.
In 7 rounds,
you'll have conflicts
with each of your neighbors
at most twice.
So there can be
at most 6 rounds in which you
have conflicts with someone.
In 7 rounds you'll find
at least one round that is
completely conflict-free.
And then we are done
and we can stop!
That's the whole algorithm.
Pick any prime number q
that is more than two times
the maximum number of neighbors.
And in q rounds, you can turn
a coloring with q² colors into
a coloring with only q colors.
And if we combine this with
the other building blocks
that we have in this week's
course material,
we will get an algorithm that
finds a coloring with Δ+1 colors
in any graph of maximum degree Δ,
and the running time is
O(log* n + Δ).