Today we will look
at the following question:
what can you do at best
in T rounds in the LOCAL model?
We didn't restrict
message size,
we didn't restrict
local computation.
So in each round everyone
could tell everything they know
to all of their neighbors!
And this is also the best thing
that you could do,
you can't tell something
you don't know,
and telling less won't help.
Let's see what this means.
Before the first round
each node knows only
its own identifier
and its own degree and
whatever local inputs it had.
So basically you know
only your radius-0 neighborhood.
And this is all that you can
tell your neighbors in round 1.
But now if everyone
tells this to each neighbor,
everyone will know
who their neighbors are.
So after 1 round,
all nodes are aware of their
radius-1 neighborhoods.
And in the second round
everyone will tell this
to all their neighbors.
So everyone will learn
what is the radius-1
neighborhood of each neighbor.
And if you put together
this information,
you will have a full picture
of your radius-2 neighborhood!
And you can continue this way.
After round 3, everyone knows
their radius-3 neighborhood.
After round 4, everyone knows
their radius-4 neighborhood.
And so on.
So at best in T rounds
you can learn everything
up to distance T,
and nothing more.
And if you stop after T rounds
and announce your local output,
then whatever you output
has to be a function
of the information
that was there
in the network within
distant T from you.
So now we have another
equivalent way
to define algorithms
in the LOCAL model:
an algorithm that runs
in time T is simply a mapping
from radius-T neighborhoods
to local outputs!
This means that
time and distance are
interchangeable
in the LOCAL model.
And therefore
fast distributed algorithms
are also highly localized.
If we have a fast algorithm,
each node makes decisions
based on the information
that was available
in its local neighborhood.
So let's recap,
all these notions are
the same in the LOCAL model:
What is the running time?
Or how many communication
rounds are needed?
Or what is the locality
of the problem?
Or how far do you need
to see in the graph?
Something as simple as
coloring a path with 2 colors
is an example of
a global problem.
Let's quickly prove it.
Assume you had some way of
solving it in sublinear time.
So along a long path,
these two nodes could pick
their own colors based on
the information in their
local neighborhood only.
Let's assume the distance
between the nodes is even,
so they pick the same color,
let's say black.
But let's then modify
the input graph like this.
We just move this one node
to a new place,
keep everything else the same,
including all unique identifiers.
These two local neighborhoods
don't change.
So the local outputs of these
two nodes won't change, either.
So both nodes will still output
the same color.
But the distance between
the nodes is now odd,
so somewhere along the path
the coloring can't be right.
So any sublinear-time
algorithm will fail.
Linear-time brute force algorithms
are the only possibility here.