Hi everyone,
Already in the first week of
this course we saw that
in the LOCAL model
it is possible to color
a directed cycle with 3 colors
in log-star many rounds.
We can start with
the unique identifiers,
which form a coloring with
a polynomial number of colors.
And then we repeatedly
reduce the number of colors.
In one round we can reduce
the number of colors from
2^k colors to only 2k colors.
And if we repeat this for
log-star many times,
the number of colors will be
a small constant.
But is this the best
that we can do?
For example, could there be
a clever way to find
a 3-coloring in constant time,
independent of the number
of nodes in the network?
This week we will see
that the answer is "no".
And we will use round
elimination to show that.
In a sense, we will show
almost the exact opposite of
what we saw in the first week.
In the first week,
we saw that if you can
find a coloring
with 2^k colors
in T − 1 rounds, then
you can find a coloring with
2k colors in T rounds.
Now using round elimination
we can work backwards,
we just lose
a factor of two here.
Basically we show that
if you can find
a coloring with k colors
in T rounds,
then you can also find
a coloring with 2^k colors
in T − 1 rounds.
And now the high-level
idea is this.
We start with
some hypothetical algorithm
that finds a proper
3-coloring in T rounds,
where T is much less
than log-star.
Then we repeat round
elimination for T times,
and we get an algorithm that
finds a c-coloring in 0 rounds.
Here c is, roughly speaking
a power tower of height T, and
if T is much less than log-star,
then c will be much less than n.
Notice that this is
a nontrivial coloring.
For example, unique identifiers
won't give such a coloring.
So we can show that this
isn't possible in 0 rounds.
So we have a contradiction
and conclude that
3-coloring cannot be done in
less than log-star many rounds.
Well, that's the idea at least.
Too bad we can't do it
directly like this.
The way we described round
elimination in the previous weeks,
it can only be applied
in the PN model.
We can't do round elimination
in the LOCAL model.
And there is a good
reason for that.
Round elimination heavily
relies on independence.
You consider
all possible inputs here.
And all possible inputs here.
And conclude that also
all possible combinations
of these inputs are possible.
But if you have unique
identifiers, this no longer holds.
Identifier 1 might be here,
or here,
but not in both places
simultaneously.
So we can't directly do round
elimination in the LOCAL model.
We have to get there indirectly.
We will first consider randomized
algorithms in the PN model.
In the lecture notes,
we will see how to do
round elimination
for randomized PN algorithms.
We will need to be
a bit more careful.
A randomized algorithm A0
for solving problem X0 still
implies a randomized algorithm A1
that solves X1 one round faster.
But we lost something,
the probability that A1 fails
will be somewhat higher than
the probability that A0 fails.
Fortunately it isn't
too bad in our application.
We can still conclude that
if we had a randomized algorithm
that finds a 3-coloring
in less than log-star time
and works with high probability,
then we will get
a randomized algorithm
that finds a coloring with
less than n colors in 0 rounds
and still has got a pretty good
success probability.
So good that we can rule out
the existence of such algorithms.
So we have now a negative result
for 3-coloring
in the randomized PN model.
But we wanted to understand it
in the LOCAL model.
Well, if you had
a fast randomized algorithm A
for the LOCAL model
that you would like to run
in the PN model,
you could first pick large
enough random labels
and use them as
unique identifiers.
So you could simulate A
in the randomized PN model.
And you would get an equally fast
randomized PN algorithm this way,
with almost the same
success probability.
And we concluded that
randomized PN algorithms
can't run in sub-log-star time,
so the same has to hold for
randomized LOCAL algorithms, too!
And now we are already done.
Deterministic LOCAL algorithms
are just a special case of
randomized LOCAL algorithms,
so they can't find coloring
in sub-log-star time, either.
So this is the high-level plan
that we are following this week.
There are fairly many technicalities
we need to worry about,
but the good news is that once
you learn to use these tools,
you can apply the same ideas in
the study of many other problems:
First use round elimination
to prove a negative result
in the deterministic PN model.
Then take into account
probabilities
to prove the same result
for randomized PN algorithms.
And then you can easily conclude
that the same result also holds
for the LOCAL model,
both for randomized and
deterministic algorithms.