Hi everyone,
Two weeks ago
we learned how to find
a coloring with Δ+1 colors
with a deterministic algorithm.
The running time was
O(Δ + log* n).
Now we will solve the same problem
with a randomized algorithm.
The running time will be simply
O(log n), with high probability.
The algorithm and
its analysis are really easy.
Let's start with the simplest
possible idea one could imagine.
Each node just checks
which colors are currently free
in its local neighborhood.
Then each node picks a random
color from the set of free colors.
And then it checks
if there were any conflicts.
If I managed to pick a color
different from the colors
of my neighbors, I can stop.
Now this sounds
really promising,
but when you try to analyze it,
it's not so simple any more.
So let's make a tiny change
in the algorithm.
Running nodes flip coins
to decide if they are active
in this round.
And only active nodes try
to pick random free colors.
And you keep your color
if you are successful.
That's it,
this is the whole algorithm!
And it's clear that
if it ever stops,
coloring has to be proper.
But why does it stop fast,
with high probability?
It turns out it's enough
to prove the following claim:
if at any point you consider
any node that is still running,
it will stop in this round
with probability at least 1/4.
This holds for any graph,
for any node, and
for any communication round,
no matter what other nodes
have already done!
And this means that
the probability that
a given node is still running
after T rounds gets
exponentially small.
And then it isn't hard to see
that after only a logarithmic
number of rounds,
with high probability
not only this node but also
all other nodes have stopped.
So the interesting part
is this lemma.
How to prove it?
Well, let's imagine
I'm a node somewhere
in the middle of the graph.
Let's say I have got k neighbors
that are still running.
But because I had originally
more colors than neighbors,
there have to be still more than
k colors left to choose from.
Now what's the probability
that I can stop in this round?
Let's first consider
what happens if I'm active.
Now the only reason why I might
not stop is that I would pick
a random free color that
conflicts with one of my neighbors.
We will first consider
one specific neighbor v.
We have no idea
how many neighbors and
how many free colors
v has got.
But we don't care
about that, either.
In the algorithm,
I'm making my random choices
simultaneously
in parallel with v.
But to analyze what happens,
we can imagine that
I roll dice first and
v rolls dice after that,
or vice versa.
So let's do the analysis so that
v makes its random choices first,
and see what's the probability
that my choice conflicts with it.
With probability one half,
v is passive and doesn't
do anything, no conflicts.
With probability one half,
v is active
and it picks some color.
But I had more than
k free colors to choose from.
At most one of those can be
the color picked by v.
So the probability
that I make a choice
that conflicts with v
is less than 1/k.
So overall the probability that
v is active and managed to pick
a color that conflicts with me
is less than 1/(2k).
This was for
a specific neighbor v.
I have got k neighbors, and
using the union bound
we quickly get that
the probability that
at least one of them conflicts
with me is
less than k times 1/(2k),
which is less than one half.
So if I'm active,
I'll have a conflict with
probability less than one half.
So I'll stop with probability
more than one half.
And I was active
with probability one half,
so overall I'll stop with
probability more than 1/4.
And this is exactly
what we wanted to prove!
So the algorithm was this,
flip coins to decide
if you are active, and
then pick a random free color.
Now I recommend that you go back
to this earlier algorithm idea
that I showed first
where everyone is active.
What would happen
if your tried to do
exactly the same analysis
for this algorithm?
What kind of a running time
would you get?