Hello everyone,
Today we will talk about
the all-pairs shortest path
problem, or APSP for short.
The problem is simply this:
everyone needs to know
their distance to everyone else.
This is the ultimate
routing primitive.
You have got some data
to send to any destination,
you now know how far
the destination is from you.
And if you also have got
this information
for all of your neighbors,
then you'll also immediately know
which way to forward the data
so that you move it
closer to the destination.
It will be useful to contrast
the all-pairs shortest path
problem with a much easier task,
single-source shortest path
problem, or SSSP for short.
Here you've got a special
starting node s,
and it is enough that everyone
knows their distance to s.
This is enough if you are
for example only routing data
towards some sink node s.
Now how do we solve these problems
in a distributed setting?
In the familiar LOCAL model,
we could trivially solve
both of these problems
in O(diameter) many rounds.
Just gather everything and
then all nodes know
the entire input graph
and they can locally compute
distances to all other nodes.
But this is heavily
abusing the assumption
that in one round we can send
arbitrarily large messages.
This week we're studying
a new model, the CONGEST model,
which is exactly the same as
the LOCAL model,
except for one restriction:
messages have to be small.
So we can no longer send
messages that contain,
for example, a full description
of the entire input graph.
We can only send around
small numbers,
for example, unique identifiers
or distances.
So how to solve APSP
in the CONGEST model fast?
As a warm-up,
let's look at single-source
shortest paths first.
This turns out to be really
simple also with small messages.
If you have specified
one node as the source,
you can simply flood
information about distances
from this node to everyone.
The node itself knows
it's at distance 0, and
it just sends a small message
to each neighbor
informing that they are
at distance 1,
they inform their neighbors that
they are at distance at most 2,
and so on.
When a node first receives
message x from any neighbor,
it knows it is at distance x,
it can inform its
other neighbors and stop.
Basically, we create waves
that propagate at constant speed
in the graph outwards, until
they have reached all nodes.
This works fine,
for any given starting point,
and it takes only
O(diameter) many rounds
until everyone knows
their distances to the source.
Now what we could try to do
is to do the same thing
for every possible source,
in sequence.
The first challenge
would be figuring out
how to coordinate this,
as we'd need to take turns
in some distributed manner.
But even worse,
even if we could do this,
it would take
n times diameter many rounds
if we initiate one wave,
wait for it to reach everyone,
and only then launch
the second wave.
Now another idea would be to
try to do all this in parallel.
Just initiate a wave starting
from each node simultaneously.
Each node tells all its neighbors
the distance to itself,
plus its identifier, and
this information is forwarded.
We'd have n waves
in progress simultaneously.
Well, if this was the LOCAL
model, it would be just fine.
But in the CONGEST model
this won't work.
There would be
potentially huge congestion
at some communication links.
We might have almost n waves
that would like to
make progress
over the same edge.
And if we somehow take turns
between different waves,
we'd increase the running time
by a factor of n
and we are back to something
like n times diameter.
But we can do better!
There is a linear-time algorithm
for finding all-pairs shortest
paths in the CONGEST model,
and it's really simple.
I'd like to emphasize we won't
get diameter time this way,
but at least the running time
will be linear in n,
and not something like
n times diameter.
So what do we do.
We first pick a leader s and
construct a tree rooted at s.
This is pretty easy to do fast
in the CONGEST model,
as we can for example first
find the node s with
the smallest identifier,
and then initiate a wave
from s to form the tree.
Here is a neat way to do
both of these in one step.
Everyone first thinks
they are leaders and
start to construct trees
rooted at them.
And then we just ignore messages
coming from one root if we have
already seen messages coming from
a root with a smaller identifier.
Basically we initiate n waves,
but other waves just die out
as they get ignored and the one
initiated by the node with
the smallest identifier wins.
There's no congestion
on any link:
in each round each node only
forwards the wave
related to the smallest root
it has seen so far.
Good, we have now somehow
picked a leader and
formed a tree rooted at it.
Now how do we use this?
The basic idea is simple.
We create n waves,
one starting at each node.
But we do it so that
many waves can be
in progress simultaneously,
without any congestion!
To do this, we initiate a token
and move it around in the tree.
The token will traverse the tree
in a depth-first manner.
Visit new children
if any are left.
Otherwise come back
towards the root.
And we do this at half speed.
Move token.
Wait for one round.
This will be important.
Now please note that
this token will traverse
the entire tree in linear time.
Roughly 4n steps are needed
until we have visited all nodes.
And what do we do
with this token?
The idea is really simple.
When we visit a new node,
we initiate a wave there.
And that's it.
We create n waves,
one per node.
And we managed to create
all the waves in linear time.
And each wave takes only
diameter time
to propagate through
the network.
So if there are no collisions
between the wavefronts,
everything will be nice and
smooth and everyone will
learn their distance to
everyone else in linear time.
And if you look at
this animation,
you'll see something curious.
The wavefronts are always
properly nested.
A new wave will never cross
a wave created earlier.
There is no congestion, we have
always got enough bandwidth
on each edge to forward
new distance information.
And this was just
a random network,
not specifically constructed
so that this would happen.
The algorithm guarantees that
two wavefronts that it creates
will never collide.
Can you see why this is
always the case?