Hello everyone,
So far we have focused
on the positive:
what can be computed
with distributed algorithms.
Now we will look
at the negative:
what cannot be computed
with distributed algorithms.
We will start with
the port numbering model.
This is a weak model,
and there are lots of problems
that cannot be solved at all
in the port-numbering model.
And this week we'll learn
a very powerful technique
for proving such results.
The key concept is called
covering maps.
You'll find the precise
mathematical definition
in the lecture notes,
but in this short video
I'll try to explain the
intuition behind this approach.
Let's look at some port-numbered
network N, like this one here.
And imagine you've got
some deterministic
distributed algorithm A.
It doesn't matter
what the algorithm does,
or what problems it solves.
It's enough that it's
a well-defined algorithm
in our formalism,
there's an init function, send
function, and receive function.
Now once you fix
algorithm A and network N,
you have also uniquely defined
the execution of the algorithm.
You can just simulate
the algorithm here and
see what messages nodes
send in each round
and how they update
their states.
You can find out, for example,
what's the state of
node a after round 5.
OK, good.
Now let's take two identical
copies of the network.
We duplicated
all nodes and all edges.
Let's call this new network X.
Now we run the same algorithm A
in network X.
What happens?
Well, obviously
we'll get exactly the same thing
as in network N,
everything was just doubled.
So if in network N
in round 5 node a sent
message m to its first port,
then in network X
in round 5 node a1 sends
the same message m to its
first port, and so does node a2.
And whatever was
the state of node a
after round 5 in network N,
then the states of a1 and a2
are going to be the same.
OK, this was of course trivial.
Now comes the interesting part.
Let's modify X slightly.
Let's, for example, replace
these two straight edges
with edges that go across.
And let's run algorithm A
in this new network Y.
Now what happened?
Well, if you think about it,
before the first round
all nodes in Y
have the same states
as the corresponding nodes in X.
And therefore all nodes also
send the same messages
in the first round
in X and in Y.
And the messages sent by a1
and a2 were identical in X,
and so were the messages
sent by b1 and b2.
So if you just look at
what messages the nodes receive
in the first round,
you won't see any differences
between X and Y.
For example, it doesn't matter
if the message b1 received
came from a1 or a2,
as both of the nodes
were identical,
they were in the same state,
and they sent the same messages.
So everyone received
the same messages in X and Y,
and hence everyone in Y
ended up in the same states
as the corresponding nodes of X
after the first round.
Whatever was the state of a1
in X after one round
is equal to the state of a1
in Y after one round.
And we can repeat the same
reasoning for each round.
Before the second round,
nodes a1 and a2 in Y were
in the same states as
nodes a1 and a2 in X,
and both of them were in
the same state as node a in N.
So they send the same messages,
and therefore
it doesn't matter whether
we are in network X or Y.
So during the second round
all nodes in Y receive
the same messages
as the corresponding nodes in X,
and they end up
in the same states.
To summarize, after each round,
nodes a1 and a2 in Y
are in the same state
as nodes a1 and a2 in X,
which are in the same state
as node a in N.
Basically, if we imagine that
we run algorithm A
simultaneously in parallel
in these three networks, we will
see exactly the same messages,
and exactly the same state
transitions
between corresponding nodes.
And if, for example,
a1 in Y ever stops
and produces some output,
then all these other nodes
will also stop in the same round
and produce the same output.
So no matter which algorithm you
use, no matter how clever it is,
it can't tell the difference
between networks N, X, and Y.
It can't tell the difference
between nodes a1 and a2 in X.
And it can't tell the difference
between a1 and a2 in Y.
So if your task is to,
for example,
tell if a connected graph has
got 4 or 8 nodes,
this is not solvable at all.
Or if you need to label
nodes in this graph
with unique identifiers,
you can't do it in
the port numbering model at all.
Formally, what you saw here is
an example of covering maps.
In this case there is
a covering map from X to N,
and also a covering map
from Y to N.
And we can show that whenever
there is a covering map
between two networks, then no
matter which algorithm you run,
the node and its image will be in
the same state after each round.
The proof is basically what
you already saw in this video:
we just argue that
the nodes are in the same states
before each round, so they
send the same messages,
and therefore they also
receive the same messages
and it follows that their
new states are also identical.
The punchline is that
covering maps
preserve everything
in port-numbered networks.
They preserve
the original local states,
they preserve outgoing messages,
they preserve incoming messages,
and therefore they also preserve
new local states for all nodes.