Welcome to the
Distributed Algorithms course
at Aalto University!
I'm Jukka Suomela and
I'm teaching this course
together with Juho Hirvonen.
Hello everyone, I'm Juho Hirvonen,
welcome also on my behalf!
In this course we will study
theoretical computer science
from a new perspective.
Imagine you are a node
in the middle of a large graph.
For example, think about
a computer network:
each node is a computer,
each edge is a communication link.
Or maybe it's a social network:
each node is a human being, and
there are edges between
two people who know each other.
Or maybe it's
a multicellular organism:
each node is a cell, and
there is an edge between two cells
that can exchange biochemical
signals with each other.
No matter what's
the specific scenario,
we will represent it as a graph,
in the usual mathematical sense.
There is a set of nodes,
and there is a set of edges.
And working together,
the nodes are trying
to accomplish something.
Maybe we need to find a tree
that can be used
for spreading information,
for routing, and for navigation.
Or maybe we need to form pairs for
collaboration and sharing resources.
Or maybe we need to find
a coloring of the nodes.
That is, label the nodes
with colors so that neighboring
nodes have different colors.
Why would we need to do this?
It turns out that coloring
is a very important primitive
especially in distributed systems.
A coloring gives a schedule.
For example, here we have
a coloring with three colors,
red, green, and blue.
We can first make red nodes active,
all other nodes are passive.
Notice that the red nodes
form an independent set.
If you look at any active node,
all of its neighbors are passive.
So we will never have two
active nodes next to each other.
Active nodes can safely do
whatever they want,
without any risk that
the actions of their neighbors
would conflict with them.
Then we can make green nodes active,
all other nodes are passive.
Then blue nodes are active,
all other nodes passive.
And now we are done, each node
had an opportunity to be active.
If we have a coloring with k colors,
we can go through all color
classes in k time steps this way.
So a coloring gives a schedule
that we can use to coordinate
the actions of the nodes.
And a coloring with a small
number of colors is good,
because it gives a short schedule;
we can complete work quickly.
So let's recap.
We have a graph that
consists of nodes and edges.
The nodes need to work together
to accomplish something.
And we are
theoretical computer scientists,
so we interpret this so that
the nodes need to solve
some computational problem.
Usually it's a graph problem.
Finding a spanning tree.
Finding a matching.
Finding a proper vertex coloring.
And so on.
And we take
a distributed perspective.
Initially, each node is
only aware of itself.
And eventually
each node needs to figure out
its own part of the solution.
For example,
if we do graph coloring,
each node needs to know
its own color.
Let's go through this more
carefully, this is critical.
This is the key difference
between the theory of
distributed computing and
the theory of classical,
centralized sequential computing.
As I said, in the beginning
each node is only aware of itself.
Nobody knows the whole graph.
Here I know that I'm here a node
with five neighbors, that's it.
I can exchange messages
with my neighbors to learn more.
And of course
all other nodes can do the same.
Everyone can talk to their
own neighbors to learn more.
But we don't want to waste
too much time doing communication.
Each communication step
takes some time.
And we want to minimize
the number of communication rounds.
So after some, ideally small
number of communication rounds
we want to stop.
And when we stop,
each node has to figure out
its own part of the solution.
If we are forming pairs,
each node needs to know which
of the neighbors is its pair.
If we do graph coloring,
each node needs to know
its own color.
And this is already enough for
each node to know what to do.
For example, if we use
graph coloring for scheduling,
if I know that my color is five,
I know that
I can be safely active
during time slot number five.
I don't need to know
everyone's colors,
knowing my own color is enough
to know when to act.
So this is what we study
in distributed algorithms.
We are solving graph problems
so that all nodes
take part in the computation.
Both input and output
are distributed.
Nobody knows the whole input.
And each node only needs to know
its own part of the output.
This is very different
from classical theoretical
computer science, where
we think that the whole input
is stored in one place,
it is given to one computer
to be processed,
and the whole output
is then returned back.
Usually we don't even pay
any attention to this,
but please note that this is
a very strong assumption.
We assume someone knows perfectly
the entire state of the world!
Someone knows the structure
of the whole Internet,
or the structure of the global
social network, and so on.
Also please note that
this is different from
traditional parallel computing,
where we may use multiple
processors to solve the problem,
but we nevertheless have
the full input stored
somewhere in one place
and eventually we will store
the whole solution in one place.
So in pretty much all other
areas of computer science
you take an outsider's view.
You are an all-seeing entity,
sitting somewhere outside your input.
You know everything.
The only question is what
to do with this information.
While in distributed algorithms
we take an insider's view.
We are sitting somewhere
in the middle of a graph,
we are one of possibly
millions of nodes.
And we have no idea
about the whole input.
We can learn a bit more
by talking to our neighbors.
But since we'd like to
solve problems fast,
we usually don't want to wait
until everyone knows everything.
So we'd like to be able to
produce at least our own part of
the solution based on whatever
we see in our local neighborhood.
And this turns out to be one of
the key concept that we want to
understand in this course:
locality.
Fast distributed algorithms are
necessarily highly localized.
In a small number of
communication steps you can only
get some information
from your local neighborhood.
Why is this?
Well, just imagine an algorithm
where in each round everyone
tells all of its neighbors
everything it knows so far.
Initially, everyone
just knows about itself.
Then after one round
everyone knows about everything
within distance one.
After two rounds
everyone knows about everything
within distance two.
After three rounds
everyone knows about everything
within distance three.
And so on.
So in T rounds everyone can know
at best everything up to
distance T, and nothing more.
If you stop after
a small number of rounds,
whatever you output
will only depend on
what you see close to you.
Fast distributed algorithms are
necessarily also highly localized.
And this is a key questions
we are going to ask,
over and over again
during this course:
When is this enough?
What can you do
with only local information?
And what cannot be
solved locally?
Which graph problems are local?
And which graph problems
are global?
Or put otherwise,
which problems can be solved
fast in a distributed setting,
with only a small number of
communication rounds?
And which problems necessarily
require a large number of rounds?
So you can approach
these questions
from a purely graph-theoretic
perspective if you prefer that.
Or you can think about computers,
network connections,
messages that you pass
between nodes,
and algorithms that process
the messages, and so on.
Whichever you do,
you will get a new perspective
on the theory of computing.
You will learn
to think like an insider,
instead of thinking
like an outsider.
So far in many other courses
you have been reasoning about
computational operations.
Like, how many arithmetic
operations or memory lookups
or Turing machine steps
are needed to solve something.
The key resource
has been computation.
In this course we will study
an entirely different kind of
resource: communication.
We will look at questions like
how many communication steps
are needed to solve something.
And, if you look at
real-world computer networks
in practice,
you can see that communication
steps are usually very expensive
in comparison with
computational steps.
If you just try to get one bit
of data from another computer
sitting in your local network,
it'll take something like
half a millisecond.
Half a millisecond
may not sound like much,
until you check how many
arithmetic operations
your computer could do
in half a millisecond.
And even for your
old desktop computer
the answer can be easily
one billion!
So there can be a factor
one billion difference
between the cost talking to
other computers
and doing some number-crunching
inside one computer!
So if you have a bunch of nodes
that are sitting in a network
and that want to solve
something together,
the key limitation is often
communication, not computation.
And this is one of
the key reasons
why I want to make sure
you learn
how to design algorithms that
are communication-efficient.
And we will also learn how to
prove negative results
that tell us about
the fundamental limitations of
computation in large networks.
We will learn how to prove
that some problems
are inherently global;
we show that there is no way to
solve them in a small number of
communication rounds, by using
only local information around you.
And such results tell us something
fundamental about nature,
as they apply to any system that
consists of entities
that talk to each other.
Not just about man-made systems,
like telecommunication networks.
We can use the same principles to
reason about biological systems
or social networks.
We can apply what we learn here
to study job markets
or animal populations.
In particular, we can use
what we learn here to study
the fundamental limitations
of such systems:
what are things that
you cannot do quickly,
no matter what kind of
a mechanism we use.
So distributed computing
is not only about computers,
it is very much about
understanding the
mathematical foundations of
all kinds of systems that
consist of interacting entities.