Let's say we want to prove that
solving some problem X requires,
for example,
at least 5 communication rounds.
We could, in principle,
do this as follows:
Consider any algorithm A
that runs in 4 rounds.
Then show that algorithm A
fails to solve X.
But it's often very hard
to reason about
what an algorithm might do
in 4 rounds.
Of course a 4-round algorithm
is just a mapping
from radius-4 neighborhoods
to local outputs.
But there is a huge number
of possible mappings.
How could we argue that
all of them will fail?
It would be much easier
to argue that X can't be
solved in 0 rounds.
0-round algorithms are
very restrictive.
There are not
that many possibilities;
it is often very quick to show
that a 0-round algorithm
will necessarily fail.
But how do we connect these two?
We'd like to prove that
4-round algorithms will fail.
We can easily prove that
0-round algorithms will fail.
We will apply here a technique
called round elimination.
We start with problem X0.
We assume that
there is an algorithm A0
that solves X0 in 4 rounds.
We apply round elimination to X0.
We get a new problem X1.
And if our assumption is right,
we also get an algorithm A1
that solves X1 in 3 rounds.
We eliminated one round
in the running time.
Notice that X1 is
a different problem.
We are interested in X0,
but we got a new problem X1.
But let's not worry about this.
We can just continue.
We apply round elimination to X1.
We get a new problem X2.
And if our assumptions are right,
we also get an algorithm A2
that solves X2 in 2 rounds.
Repeat.
We get a new problem X3.
And we also get an algorithm A3
that solves X3 in 1 round.
Repeat.
We get a new problem X4.
And we also get an algorithm A4
that solves X4 in 0 rounds.
And now this is what we wanted.
Assuming X0 can be solved
in 4 rounds,
we can solve X4 in 0 rounds.
And now it is enough to show that
X4 can't be solved in 0 rounds.
If we can show that all possible
0-round algorithms for X4 fail,
then we have a contradiction.
Therefore
X3 can't be solved in 1 round.
X2 can't be solved in 2 rounds.
X1 can't be solved in 3 rounds.
X0 can't be solved in 4 rounds.
And this is exactly
what we wanted to prove.
Of course there is nothing magic
about the value 4 here.
If we can do 10 steps of
round elimination and
still arrive at a problem that
is not 0-round solvable, we know
that the original problem
cannot be solved in 10 rounds.
If we can do any number of
round elimination steps,
then the original problem cannot
be solved in constant time.
And so on.
So to recap, round elimination
is a technique that turns
a problem X0 into a new problem X1
that can be solved 1 round faster.
It can only be used when
a problem is in the right form.
We must have a so-called bipartite
locally verifiable problem.
Few problems are directly
given in this form,
but many problems can be turned
into this form,
and then
round elimination works.
Informally, if the problem is
defined in terms of local
constraints, it is good.
For example, graph coloring
is such a problem.
There is a constraint
on each edge:
the endpoints must have
different colors.
And there are
no other constraints.
If a coloring looks good
in all local neighborhoods,
then it is indeed
a valid solution.
A maximal independent set
is also something you can
define using local constraints.
Independence can be checked
by looking at each edge.
Maximality can be checked
by looking
at the local neighborhood
of each node.
On the other hand,
connectivity and acyclicity
are global properties,
so we can't study problems like
spanning trees using these tools.
OK, so
what does a "bipartite locally
verifiable problem" look like?
We will look at problems
in regular trees.
But this isn't usually
any real restriction,
as we are trying
to prove negative results.
If we can show that
the problem can't be solved
fast in regular trees,
then certainly
it can't be solved fast
in general graphs.
And it turns out that
regular trees are the worst case
for many problems.
In the lecture notes you'll
find the general definitions,
here I'll just give one example.
This is a problem
that we call weak 3-labeling.
This problem is defined in trees
in which nodes are partitioned
in two roles:
active and passive.
These roles form a proper
2-coloring of the tree.
Each edge is connecting
an active node and a passive node.
We will ignore the leaf nodes.
They are unconstrained.
We only care about what happens
in the middle of the tree.
And here all active nodes
have degree 3, and
all passive nodes
have degree 2.
And what is the task.
Each active node has to label
its incident edges
with colors red, green, and blue.
And there are two constraints.
Active nodes must
not be monochromatic.
That is, all three edges
around an active node
can't have the same color.
For example, this is good.
And so is this.
But this is forbidden.
Conversely, passive nodes must
be monochromatic.
Both of the edges
around a passive node
must have the same color.
For example, this is good.
But this is forbidden.
Now this is problem X0.
We would like to understand
how fast this can be solved.
It's easy to check that this
can't be solved in 0 rounds.
Active nodes must use
at least two different colors.
But then if you do it
without any coordination,
there is a risk that
a passive node gets
two incident edges
with different colors.
Let's do round elimination once
and see what's the problem X1 we get.
You can look at the lecture notes
for how to do it with pen and paper,
or you can just ask computers.
Either way,
we will get this problem.
It's very similar
to what we already had;
it turns out we basically just
swapped the roles of
active and passive nodes.
Again, it's easy to check that
this can't be solved in 0 rounds.
Active nodes must use
the same color for both
of their incident edges.
And if you apply
any deterministic rule,
the only possible algorithm is
something like
"color everything red".
And this will clearly fail.
So we already know something.
X1 can't be solved in 0 rounds.
So the original problem X0
can't be solved in 1 round.
You need at least 2 rounds
to solve X0.
Let's do round elimination
again, now we'll get problem X2.
Now this problem is something
lot more interesting.
Here is one interpretation of it.
In this problem your task is to
label edges with sets of colors.
Active nodes have
the following constraint:
there has to be one set that
doesn't contain red,
one set that
doesn't contain green,
and one set that
doesn't contain blue.
So for example this is fine.
And so is this.
But this isn't.
Here we have got
green in all sets.
Passive nodes have
the following constraint:
the sets must have
a non-empty intersection.
So for example this is fine.
And this.
But this isn't,
there are no common elements.
Now, can you solve
this problem in 0 rounds?
This takes some thought,
but it turns out it is possible!
Active nodes can always
pick a solution like this:
red-green on one edge,
red-blue on one edge,
green-blue on one edge.
Why is this good?
Well, it's clearly fine
for active nodes,
as for each color there's
one set that doesn't contain it.
And it's also fine
for passive nodes!
If you get some
two-element set here
and another
two-element set here,
no matter what they are,
they have to contain
some common element.
Like here.
Or here.
So X2 is solvable in 0 rounds,
while X1 isn't.
It turns out this means that
the complexity of X1
is exactly 1 round.
And the complexity of X0
is exactly 2 rounds.
Now how do you solve X0
in 2 rounds?
We can work backwards!
We start with
a 0-round algorithm for X2,
and spend 1 round to turn
it into a solution for X1.
And then another round to turn
it into a solution for X0.
You will fill in the details
in one of this week's exercises!